This is the company with the largest market share in the health insurance industry in India.
But there are just as many complaints about this
.  With this option,
your premiums will
not increase even as your age increases.  They are always fixed
.  These two options mean that
even if we have health insurance, we will still have to
pay money out of our own pocket.  The bill
amount will be around 100,000.  But they only
settled for 2230,000.
In the financial year 2022 alone,
13,000 plus complaints
were registered against them.  Star Names is our
performance in Hello Asset Tribe
Welcome Back to Another Interesting
Video.  In today's video, we are going to break down a popular health
insurance scheme in detail
.  That's Star
Health Insurance.  Star Health
Insurance is the largest
stand-alone health insurance
player in India.  This means that they do not sell
vehicle
insurance and property insurance like other general insurance players
.  The majority of the business
is focused on health insurance.  And this Star Health's
presence is very strong not only in tier one cities
but also in tier 2 and tier three cities
.   The
reason for this is Star Health's 7
lakh plus agent network.  Overall,
Star Health has the
largest market share among private health insurance players in India and the
features in the plans they offer are also quite
unique.  Like Freeze
Your Age, this is an option that allows you to continue paying the
same premiums without increasing your annual premiums
.
Also, all the necessary features like maternity cover, renewal bonus, and
restoration benefits
are available in these plans.  That's why many people
also check Star Health when considering getting health insurance.  But
as much as there are positives related to this company, there is
also as much noise related to it in the market
.   Every
year, Star
Health Insurance news is filled with some issue, such as claims not being settled properly, or issues with hospital networks, such as IRDI imposing fines.
Therefore, instead of
blindly taking the name "Star" for granted, let's find out in detail
what the features behind this plan are, what the terms and
conditions are, whether claims are
settled, and what other details such as these actually
stand when compared to other plans
.
So, if you are holding this plan
or considering taking it,
watch this video till the end, it will
be very useful.  Because if we are
hospitalized because we have health insurance,
we don't want to
face financial stress in such a situation.
So, allocate some time and learn the
full details about this plan
.  And if this is your first time on this channel,
I am Yashwanth, I am a
Chartered Wealth Manager.  On this channel, we will
simplify complicated finance topics and present them to you
.  So if you haven't subscribed to the channel yet,
please subscribe because
many people
watch the videos but
forget to subscribe.  Please subscribe
.  Let's log in without further delay
.
This Star Health and Allied Insurance
company was started in Tamil Nadu in 2006
.  With almost 20 years of
operations, they have evolved into one of the
largest private health
insurance players in India
.  And more over it is also
listed in stock markets.  So
in terms of brand value, Star
Health has a strong presence in India
.  And they sell Star Health Insurance plans not only through their agent network but also
in many banks
.  So let
's check how Star performs among the metrics that we must definitely consider when taking out health insurance.
First Claim Settlement Ratio.
Whatever this claim settlement ratio is,
it is an important factor that we must check in the insurance world
.
What this number indicates is
what percentage of the claims the company receives are actually
settled
.  Taking
the average of the last three financial years,
Star Health's
claim settlement ratio is just 84.97%
.  This is very low compared to other top private health
insurance plans
.  If we take the other top players like
HDFC, Aditya Birla, Care and Nivabupa,
all of those companies maintain
their claim settlement ratios above 90%
.  And if you look at HDFC
's claim settlement ratio, it is
96.71%, which is the
highest claim settlement number among these companies,
but HDFC Ergo maintains it at 71%.
And lastly, there is Star Health Insurance
.  So what this number says is that
Car Health is
only settling 84% of the 100 claims they receive
.  The rest
are being rejected for various reasons.  So,
Star
Health Insurance lags behind in this important parameter, the claim settlement ratio.  And
personally I want to learn from you guys.   If
any of you have faced any Star Health related
claim issues, please
tell us in the comments section below.  That
experience will help everyone
.  And the next important
parameter we need to check is the network
hospitals Star Health has tie-ups with
almost 14,000 plus hospitals across India
.  And
their presence in major cities in Andhra Pradesh and Telangana is
also good.  While
almost 1000 plus network
hospitals are available here in Telangana,
major cities like Hyderabad, Warangal,
Khammam, and Nizamabad have this number of
hospitals.  And there are
800 plus network hospitals available in Andhra Pradesh
.
And the numbers in the top cities in Andhra Pradesh are as follows
.  Among these network
hospitals,
Star Health Insurance
maintains the highest numbers when compared to Pierce
.  In this parameter, Star Health is in
the lead when compared to other top players
.  The next thing we
need to check is the Incurred Claim
Ratio.  What this indirect claim ratio
tells us is
what percentage of the premiums received by the company are
used to settle actual claims
.  If we look at Star Health's incurred claim
ratio of 72.84%, Star Health stands in second position when
compared to the top players in this parameter
.
HDFC is in first position with 85.83%,
Aditya Bella is in third position with 67.52%,
and Care
and Nivapa are standing in fourth and fifth positions.   The
last and very important
parameter to look at is the volume of
complaints.  This parameter tells us
how many complaints are filed against the company with IRDI out of every 10,000 claims received by the company
.  This compliant
volume
is 22 if we look at an overall industry average.  Star Health
's compliant volume
is a bit shocking.  Which is
52.31, meaning that on average, out of every 10,000
claims, 52 complaints
are registered against the company.  This is
a lot compared to other top players.  In this case, HDFC and Aditya
Billa got the lowest number of
complaints per 10,000 claims and
Star Health, along with Care and Nivabupa
health insurance, are also registering
more complaints than the industry average
.  Even in this ratio,
HDFC maintains the best numbers, while
Star Health
maintains the least.  And even
after looking at the Council of Insurance Ombudsman report,
only in the 23rd and 24th financial years, around 13,000 plus
complaints were registered against Star Health
.  Which is followed by
Care and Niwabu Page and Star
Health, out of these 13,000
complaints registered, 10,000 plus
complaints are partially
settling or
rejecting the claims. The complaints registered
and personally few members shared this with me.
Unfortunately, when a cashless
claim goes for reimbursement, the
claim amount is not settled in full but is
settled partially and the case is closed
.  For
example, if we apply for a claim for an amount of 100,000, they
settle just 20 or 25,000 and close the case
.  They shared that they
fought a lot for the rest of the amount and
filed a complaint with IRDI, but the claim
was settled.  The real reason for
taking out health insurance is that if we are unfortunately
hospitalized, the insurance
company will bear all our expenses,
but if we have to stress while in the hospital for that claim amount and then have to
fight about the claim afterwards, it can be very
painful.  That's why,
especially when taking out health insurance, you should only
take it from someone who can provide strong claim support, from a right advisor.  Like ditto
insurance.  Dito got one of the best
claim support.  If you
have taken out health insurance through them,
if you are unfortunately hospitalized,
they will take care of the complete process related to your claim.  If
you book a call here at a time of your choice,
one of our IRDI certified
advisors will connect with you, clarify all your
health insurance-related
doubts, and
suggest plans that suit you.
And if you just call back after the call ends, they wo
n't spam you.  If you
like it, you can proceed, otherwise, no, because it is
completely spam-free,
and they will review any plans you have,
even if they are completely free, and
provide you with a port option if you need one.  So, if you are
thinking of getting a good health insurance for yourself or your family, check out the
free call booking link in the
description below and pin it in the comments section
.  So if
claim settlement and compliant
volume are in these two parameters, then
Star needs to level up their game.
And
if you conclude that the plan is a waste because these two parameters are not good, don't do it
.  Because the health
insurance plans they offer have unique features
and variants available to cover different age groups and diseases
.  Let's now discuss in detail what those features and variants are
.  The plans offered by Star Health are
available in around eight variants
in the market.  Of these eight variants, there are three that
we should focus on as major ones
.  They are Super Star, Star Health,
Ashur and Star Comprehensive.  These three
plants are the most sold products in the market
and in addition to these eight variants, there
are also some variants that cover specialized diseases.  But in this
video, we'll talk about the most sold variants
.
First one is the Super Star variant.  This is
Star Health Insurance's most
popular and most sold plan.
If we look at the important features of this plan,
we will not have any co-payment in this plan
.  This can be taken as an individual plan
and also as a family floater plan
.  And if you look at the room rent, there is no
room rent capping
.  There
are no disease-related supplements and in addition,
pre- and post-hospitalization charges are
also paid.  Also, day care, AYUSH
domiciliary expenses are all
included.  And free annual checkups are
not inbuilt.  For that, we will have to
purchase an additional rider again
.  And besides, the restoration
benefit is unlimited times, meaning that
even if you make any claim in a year,
that amount will be refilled immediately.  If it is
unlimited times like this, the registration
benefit will work in this plan.
And then the cumulative bonus is a claim-
free year, meaning no claims were made in a year
.  Then,
whatever our cover amount is, 50% of it will be
added as a bonus.  Let's say
you take a policy for a cover of Rs 10,000, and in case you
make any claim in that year, a
bonus of Rs 5 lakh will be
added to it for the next year.  So your overall cover
amount will be 10 lakhs to 15 lakhs
.  You can add this bonus up to 100% of your cover
amount, i.e. up to 10 lakhs
.  But only
for claim free years.  These are the
basic features available in this variant, but what we need to
discuss are the
highlighted features they offer.  The first thing we need
to talk about is Freeze Your Age.  This
feature, if any, is
only available in the Superstar variant.
How this freeze your age works is that the
premiums
are calculated based on your age when you take out the policy.
Whatever the premium is, you can continue paying the same premium in the following years
.  But once you have made a claim in any year,
this
option will not be valid from that time onwards.  Premiums will be calculated and deferred based on
your age from the next renewal year
.  For
example, let's say you purchased this plan when you were 25 years old
.  If the
premium you have to pay at that age is
₹15,000,
you can pay the same premium every year until you claim it at any time in the future, whichever is higher.
This is not usually the case with health insurance plans, where
premiums increase as age increases
.  But with this option,
your premiums remain fixed
until you make a claim.  So due to
reasons, if you claim for inpatient treatment,
AYUSH treatment
or day care treatment,
this option will
not work yet.  Premiums are calculated based on
your age from the next renewal year
.  This is how the Freeze
Your Age option works.
This feature in particular is a very
good feature because usually
when we are young, we don't make many claims. Even if
we don't make any claims for almost three or four years, we still
pay a little more in premiums
.  But with this option, premiums
are fixed.  There is no
need to pay any additional premiums
.  So, we can say that this is a definite
advantage feature for youngsters.  And
along with this freezer age feature, there are other highlighted
features as well.  The premium
waiver benefit means that if, by
any chance, we are diagnosed with a critical illness after taking this plan,
any premiums we have to pay will be waived
.  And with that,
we can easily track our heart rate, oxygen saturation, and other respiratory rates by scanning our face directly in the app, which they provide.  And in
addition to that, dental checkups have also been added to this variant
.  But it is
not possible to claim it in the first year.
These services are available to us from the second and third year onwards
.  And this
superstar variant has made
almost 21 years of additions available to us
.  When we purchase this health plan from them, we can
add the add-ons we like
.  But the only problem is that there are so many
options that it can
create a bit of confusion when choosing.  And in this Super Star
variant, almost 21 additional add-
ons have been made available to us.
We can add different add-ons to this plan, such as Quick Sheet, Unlimited Care, Reduction in Pre-Existing Diseases, Consumable Cover, or Annual Checkups.
So, with so many options, it can
create a bit of confusion when we want to buy a policy.  So if you're going to
take it, spend some time and
understand how it works before taking it
.  Don't
take it if you're worried.  These are the overall
features and benefits of this Superstar variant
.  Now let's take a look at the other two variants and
compare them in detail.
Before that, if you found the information shared so far
useful, please
like the video and drop a comment saying it's valuable
.  Because there are
many days and days of research
behind it to study so many variants and options and present them to you in a simplified way.  So don't forget to
like the video and subscribe to the channel
.  So, if we compare these three features and
look at the minimum and maximum cover amount,
we can take anything from 500,000 to unlimited in Superstar
.  In the same comprehensive plan, you
can take up to 500,000 to 1 crore.
In the same health assure,
we can take this policy for anything from 500,000 to 2 crores
.  And if
we look at the room rent limit, we can take any category room in the Super Star variant and get
the treatment then.  However, there are some limitations
in the Comprehensive and Health Assurance variants
.
Even though the restoration benefit is unlimited
for the Superstar and Health Assure variant,
this restoration is done only once a year for the Comprehensive variant.
And even though we look at free health checks,
we only get this as an optional cover in the Superstar variant
.   It is
not inbuilt.  The same applies
to Comprehensive and Health Ashore, but they
come as inbuilt.  But in the comprehensive variant,
it can be used after one claim-free year
.  In the same Health Assure
variant, health checkup expenses are paid up to ₹2,000 for an individual plan and
up to ₹5,000 for a family floater plan
.  And if you look at the disease-wise sub-limits, there are no
disease-wise sub-limits in the Super Star variant
.  But there are
some limitations in the Comprehensive and Health Assure variant
.  And there is no conflict between these three variants
.  And you can see
how the renewal bonus works in these three variants
here.  And
in all these variants, pre- and post-
hospitalization charges are paid.
In addition, there is also day care treatment coverage
.  Also, if you are taking In Case Home Care
treatment, the Super
Star variant has up to 10 locks, meaning
in this comparison we
have taken a cover of 10,000,000, so we will
pay up to 10,000,000.  However, Health Assur
only pays up to Rs. 100,000
.  And
you can see all the other features here.  And if
you look at the waiting periods, they are
equally applicable across all variants
.  But in the Super Star variant,
we can reduce these waiting periods by adding a new one
.  There are no limitations
on eye treatments in Super Star and
Health Usher,
but
there is a disease-wise supplement in Star Comprehensive.  And then if we
look at the consumables, we can add
this consumable in the Super Star variant as an additional
rider.  But
this consumable option is not available in the Comprehensive variant,
while this option is available in the Health Assure variant
.  Even if we look at the maternity cover,
we
can add it as an optional cover in the Superstar variant.
This maternity option is available at And Star Comprehensive and Health Ashore
.  But remember, if
we look at the variants with maternity cover
or take those options,
our premiums will
increase tremendously.  Remember, we will have to
pay a little more in premiums
.  And if you ever
take out health insurance,
make sure it doesn't have any disease-specific sub-limits or consumable charges.  These consumables are items that are
used once during treatment, such as
bandages, gloves, syringes,
etc. When such items
are not covered by our health insurance, we will have to
pay all these costs ourselves during the treatment period.  So after the bill is generated, we have to
pay a certain amount from our pocket.  And also disease wise
sub limits.  These disease-wise sub-limits
mean that even if the health insurance cover amount is
high, it will
only pay a certain amount for some treatments, as mentioned
in the policy document
.  Many people do
n't know this until they undergo treatment that requires admission to the hospital.
Remember that if you find out after a treatment that it is not covered or has a limitation on it, you will have to pay any additional amount out of your own pocket.  I think
this is also the reason why so many complaints are registered against Star Health
.  Because many agents sell policies
without disclosing all these conditions
.
As a result, customers who are
admitted to the hospital will face this problem
.  That's why you need to
follow an important checklist when taking out a health plan
.  Please check here if you need to check as a major
.
And if possible,
talk to the agent about everything clearly when you take it.
If possible, try to read the policy document as well
.  So,
out of these top three variants of Star Off,
Super Star seemed to be the only one that was a little
effective.  Because there
are no rumors or restrictions, there
are no disease-wise sublimits, and
we can also add consumables through riders.  These are the
details of the important variants offered by Star Health,
but along with these variants, specialized plans are also available to
cover specialized diseases like cancer
, diabetes, cardiac
care, and women
.  Let's discuss them in more
detail in another video
.
But these are the variants that should be focused on as a major.  Now
let's jump into the pros and cons.  So if
you look at the pros of Star Health, they
provide a very good network of hospitals as well as unique features in their plans.  And
they also make restoration benefits and no-claim bonuses available
.  And in case you need maternity cover,
they are also
providing it as an option.  And
looking at the disadvantages, the
claim settlement
ratio they maintain is very low compared
to the industry average.  And when we
want to take out a policy, there are many
variants available.
This only creates additional confusion
.  And importantly, we need to take notice of the
high volume of complaints being registered against them.  This is
double the industry average.  And
a few months back, IRDI
also imposed a penalty of Rs 3.39 crore on Star Health.
Due to a cybersecurity breach.  So,
before we finally decide whether we should consider Star Health Insurance or not, let's compare
Star Health Insurance with HDFC, which offers the best metrics in the industry
.  And before that, please consider
any knowledge shared in this video
for educational purposes only
.  It is
not investment advice of any kind.  Metrics-wise,
HDFC Argo maintains
much better numbers than Star Health in all parameters except for network hospitals
.  Let's compare this Super Star variant, which is the best variant in Wheat Compliant
Volume or Claim Settlement Ratio
and Star Health, with the
Optima Secure variant, which is the best variant in HDFC Argo
.  If you look at this comparison, you will see that all
these features like restoration benefits, free health checkups, etc.
are also common in Star and HDFC.   But when it
comes to additional coverage,
whatever the Optima Secure variant is in HDFC Argo,
it comes with 2x coverage from day one
.  This means that if you take out 10 locks of cover,
you will have
coverage for up to 20 locks.  But Star does
n't have that option.  And also,
we can reduce the waiting period by using additional riders, if any, in both these variants
.  And if
you look at the maternity cover, it is available as an optional cover in the Superstar variant
.  But there is
no maternity cover option in HDFC Arga.  In
case you are looking at maternity coverage, you should know that there are usually
waiting periods of up to four years depending on the maternity cover option
.  In that case,
we will not be able to claim expenses related to maternity cover within those two years
.  So choosing this maternity option will
increase our premium significantly.  In
case you are considering taking it, be
sure to find out information about its related
waiting periods
.  So when
we compare Star and HDFC relatedly, we don't see any
huge differences
.  But when we
look at the metrics, we see that HDFC is in a better place
.  And we already covered a
detailed review related to HDFC Argo Health Insurance a few
months back
.  In case
you want to know more about it,
watch the video in the end cards.  So
overall, if we can consider the health insurance offered by Star Health,
we can definitely explore their feature-rich plan, Super Star
.  Before taking out a policy, don't forget to read the
policy document and
try to understand the terms and conditions contained therein.  In case you don't have that much
time, consult a trusted
advisor and
purchase the policy only after learning about its relevance
.  In case you
are looking for genuine advice, you can book a
free call with Dito Advisors, where
you will get free best plan comparisons,
premium breakdowns, and claim assistance after taking the policy
.  I'm putting the free call booking link in the
description in the comments section, so be
sure to use it
.  And not only will they review your existing
health plans for free, but
they will also help you port your health insurance to another plan if you need it.  Try using the free call
booking link in the description in the
comments section
.  And in case
you have
any good or bad experiences related to health insurance, please
try to share them in the comments section below. It will be
useful for everyone.  And before you go, don't forget to
subscribe to the channel
.  See you with another informative video,
Till Then Boy Boy.